Finding Aid for Halvor N. Christensen papers,1939-1997
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Halvor N. Christensen papers 1939-1997 1972-1995
Christensen, Halvor N.
1 linear foot
9845 Aa2
Halvor Niels Christensen was a professor and researcher in the field of biochemistry, specializing in amino acid transports. The majority of his academic career was spent at the University of Michigan where he was a professor (1955-1986) and chair (1955-1970) of the Biochemistry department. The bulk of this collection is correspondence covering 1968-1997. Also biographical material, selected articles (reprints) authored by Christensen, and photographs of Christensen and colleagues including Albert Baird Hastings and Olliver Lowry.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection received in 1998 (donor no. 8743 ) and in 2007 (donor no. 9878 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Halvor Niels Christensen was born October 24, 1915, in Cozad, Nebraska to Niels and Matena Christensen. He was the third of six children. Christensen attended the Nebraska State Teacher's College and earned a Bachelor's degree in chemistry in 1935. In 1937, he obtained his Master's in biochemistry from Purdue University, and earned his PhD in biochemistry from Harvard University in 1939.
His academic professional career began at Harvard Medical School (1942-1948), first as an instructor, and then as assistant professor in biochemistry. Christensen taught at Tufts University School of Medicine as a professor and chair of its Biochemistry Department from 1949 to 1955. He then moved to the University of Michigan where he spent the majority of his career. He was a professor (1955-1986) and chair (1955-1970) of the Department of Biological Chemistry. He retired in 1986 and was named professor emeritus. Christensen moved to La Jolla, California where he served as an adjunct professor in pediatrics at the University of California in San Diego from 1989 to 1999.
Christensen was an internationally known authority in the area of amino acid transport. He was the author of a number of books in the field of biochemistry and over 270 journal articles.
He remained active in his field well into his retirement. Christensen died on October 2, 2003, at the age of 88. He was survived by his three children, Hugh, Carl and Karen. His wife Mary died in 2003.
The bulk of the Halvor N. Christensen collection collection consists of correspondence covering the years 1968-1997. The papers also include biographical material, selected articles (reprints) authored by Christensen, and photographs of Christensen and colleagues including Albert Baird Hastings and Olliver Lowry. The collection has been divided into four series: Biographical Information, Correspondence, Articles and Reprints, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Christensen, Halvor N.; Biological transport.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Biological Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical
  Biographical Information includes a bibliography of Christensen's academic journal articles, some personal recollections about his childhood, and some brief professional information. The journal article listing is current to 1995 and is assembled from many different summaries found in his papers. The personal childhood reflection is dated 1990 and is approximately 25 pages long. The professional information includes a summary of his University of Michigan personnel record (when he arrived in 1955) and also has a ten page reflection about his time as Chair of the Biochemistry Department at the University of Michigan (as recollected in 1992).
  - Academic Journal Bibliography, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Personal Biography, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Professional Biography, 1955-1993 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The majority of the collection is found in the Correspondence series. It is a collection of letters sent to or by Christensen. It is arranged alphabetically by the last name of the correspondent. Most of the correspondence is single letters and are captured under the "General" heading. There are a handful of individuals with whom Christensen had more extensive correspondence and they have separate folders. There are also letters about specific events and they have also been separated into individual folders. Most of the correspondence relates to research areas. There are few personal letters. The bulk of the correspondence is written after his retirement in 1985. This series is not meant to be a complete account of Christensen's academic or personal correspondence.
  - A, 1977-1992 (Box 1)
  - "Biomembrane Transport" Book, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Bristol-Meyer Award, 1997 (Box 1)
  - B, 1956-1995 (Box 1)
  - C, 1972-1996 (Box 1)
  - "Crossing Boundaries" Book, 1988-1996 (Box 1)
  - D, 1988-1994 (Box 1)
  - De Cespedes, Carlos, 1989-1992 (Box 1)
  - E, 1974-1996 (Box 1)
  - F, 1972-1995 (Box 1)
  - G, 1976-1994 (Box 1)
  - Garcia-Sancho, Javier, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - H, 1980-1995 (Box 1)
  - Halvor Christensen's 70th Birthday, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Hastings, Albert Baird, 1965-1986 (Box 1)
  - Hastings, Baird (son of Albert Baird Hastings), 1988-1994 (Box 1)
  - K, 1939-1997 (Box 1)
  - L, 1971-1996 (Box 1)
  - M, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - N, 1978-1990 (Box 1)
  - O, 1971-1996 (Box 1)
  - P, 1969-1994 (Box 1)
  - R, 1970-1994 (Box 1)
  - Ronquist, Gunnar, 1989-1996 (Box 1)
  - S, 1968-1995 (Box 1)
  - Symposium Honoring Halvor Christensen, 1972 (Box 1)
  - T, 1971-1992 (Box 1)
  - U, 1976-1993 (Box 1)
  - V, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Von Winkle, Lon, 1991-1997, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - W, 1972-1995 (Box 1)
  - Y, 1984-1994 (Box 1)
  - Young, James, 1984-1993 (Box 1)
  - Unknown or first name only, 1971-1995 (Box 1)
- Articles and Reprints
  Articles and Reprints contains a portion of articles and scientific reprints of articles by Christensen. They date from 1938 to 1992 but are far from complete.
  - Articles and Reprints, 1938-1992, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Photographs
  Photographs contains pictures of Christensen alone and in group photos, as well as his colleagues Albert Baird Hastings and Olliver Lowrey. Many of the images of Baird Hastings are copies of group photographs taken at Harvard and elsewhere and were likely collected by Christensen as part his efforts to edit Hastings' life story.
  - Photographs, ca. 1930s-1995 (Box 1)